Mss.B.M93
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1829-1871; 0.25 Linear feet 1 box.; 42 items.; This is a miscellaneous collection of letters concerning geology, geological exploration of Russia, entomology, glaciers, appointments in the British Museum, Geological Society of London business, Royal Geographical Society, 
  - Biographical note, January 3, 1865; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Biographical note: specific mention of military captaincy, Silurian System, Geological Society and Royal Geographical Society presidencies. Reply sent to Mr. Delvett (?)
  - Letter to "My dear Dr. Kirk", January 31, 1866; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Regarding African research.
  - Letter to Sir William [Denison], April 7, 1867; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Left for summer holidays, arrangements for key and correspondence.
    Denison, William, Sir, 1804-1871 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", June 23, 1867; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Royal Geographical Society paper. Appreciation and an invitation.
  - Letter to Admiral Irminger, July 28, 1867; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Letter of introduction for Edward Whymper.
    Irminger, Carl, 1802–1888 -- Correspondence; Whymper, Edward, 1840-1911 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to [Henry Walter] Bates, December 10, 1867; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Belgrave Square paper. Reference to the Times.
    Bates, Henry Walter, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to [Henry Walter] Bates, December 10, 1867; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Reference to a letter from the Earl of Dunmore (?)
  - Letter to [Richard Henry] Major, March 18, 1868; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Appreciation for The Life of Prince Henry, reciprocal offer of Siluria.
    Major, Richard Henry, 1818-1891 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to [Sir Edwin Henry] Landseer, January 1, 1870; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Belgrave Square paper.
    Landseer, Edwin Henry, Sir, 1802-1873 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to [Henry Walter] Bates, January 24, 1871; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Change in handwriting may be due to a stroke.
  - Letter to [Henry Walter] Bates, March 21, 1871; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Regarding Belker's (?) letters.
  - Letter to [Henry Walter] Bates, May 18, 1871; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Geological Survey of England and Wales paper.
  - Letter to [Henry Walter] Bates, July 3, 1871; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    References a visit from the Emperor of Brazil, who inquired about Bates and [Alfred Russel] Wallace, recommends Bates make contact so he can call upon His Majesty.
  - Letter to "Dear Murchison", January 12, undated; Whewell, William, 1794-1866
    Request for books.
  - Letter to "My dear General", Monday, undated; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Regarding plans to dine together.
  - Letter to [Robert Hunt], undated; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Regarding an unforwarded letter, lack of Italian topographical maps.
    Hunt, Robert,1807-1887. -- Correspondence
  - Letter to an unknown recipient, undated; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Belgrave Square paper (no earlier than 1839).
  - Letter to an unknown recipient, undated; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    Building instructions, with reference to the Jermyn Street Geological Museum.
- Series II. Reproductions, 1830-1867; 0.25 Linear feet 1 box.; 34 items, photocopies.; These are letters written from America, to Murchison, discussing geology, natural history, and contemporary topics.
  Purchased from Geological Society of London (£14.35) and accessioned, 11/24/1964 (1965 160ph).
  Existence and Location of Originals note
  Originals in Geological Society of London.
  - Table of contents, 509.G29, 1965
    List of 1964 acquisitions from the Geological Society of London.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey] Murchison, February 22, 1830; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866
    Gifts sent on the ship the Alexander from Philadelphia to Liverpool. Particular attention paid to shells and fossils, hope for samples in return. Copy of the freshly-published poem "The Deluge" (with "geological and minerological allusions") and a request for further distribution. Some general discussion of finances and will.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey] Murchison, April 14, 1830; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866
    Follow up to the earlier shipment of "Deluge" and shells. Promises to forward a forthcoming American Quarterly Review with "my notions of Geology, and of its importance."
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey] Murchison, May, 1830; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866
    Request for assistance: feedback, securing copyright.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey] Murchison, September 23, 1831; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866
    Reply to Murchison's letter from Liverpool. Appreciates feedback, will correct map as noted. Americans are "beginning to take to geology" and Featherstonhaugh plans to promote Murchison's name among them.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey] Murchison, October 28, 1831; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866
    Re: letter from Buckland, reasons why casts and writing was not presented to the Geological Society. Authenticity questioned; asks for Murchison's support.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey] Murchison, March 18, 1832; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866
    Details of fossils and casts forwarded.
  - Letter to [Sir] R[oderick] I[mpey] Murchison, May 18, 1832; Harlan, Richard, 1796-1843
    Forwarded casts, fossils, descriptions, on the advice of mutual acquaintance Featherstonhaugh.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey] Murchison, September 2, 1833; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866
    Praise for Murchison's address in the July Philosophical Magazine. Complaints about the state of American geology, subscribers' failure to pay for Featherstonhaugh's journal. Discussion of efforts in Washington.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], December 16, 1833; Lea, Isaac, 1792-1886
    Fossil samples sent (alas, not a complete collection); would be pleased to receive feedback on his writings.
  - Letter to [Sir] R[oderick] I[mpey] Murchison, April 11, 1834; Harlan, Richard, 1796-1843
    Murchison elected corresponding member of the Geological Society of Pennsylvania. Harlan's "On certain Saurian fossils discovered in the U.S." forwarded for Murchison's perusal.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], July 15, 1834; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866
    Appreciation for Murchison's introcucing him to the Geological Section of the British Association; report of United States geology for Murchison's perusal; particular interest in Murchison's work on Welsh graywacke.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], November 4, 1834; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    In French. Regarding fossils and scheduling.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey] Murchison, April 12, 1835; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866
    Introduction of the bearer, William Pitt Adams.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], July 7, 1835; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    In French. Regarding travel plans.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], October 6, 1835; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    In French. Regarding fish fossils.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], February 24, 1837; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    In French. Regarding a previous letter, a course on glaciers.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], [1838]; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    In French. Regarding travel, fish fossils.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], March 4, 1840; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    In French. Regarding Holoptychus, Old Red Sandstone ("Old Red d'Angleterre"), Silurian/Devonian organization.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], May 1, 1840; Vanuxem, Lardner.
    Regarding Murchison's letter to Silliman and interest in visiting the U.S. to examine its geology.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], November 8, 1840; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    In French. Regarding glaciers, Silurian and Devonian fish.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], May 4, 1845; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    In French. Regarding specimens from St. Petersburg, Megra, and Riga; opinions on fish and reptiles.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], May 4, 1845; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    In French. Regarding specimens from St. Petersburg, Megra, and Riga; opinions on fish and reptiles. Duplicate copy.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], January 29, 1847; Hall, James, 1811-1898
    Regarding Silurian/Cambrian boundary.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], June 12, 1847; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    In French. Regarding de Verneuil's work with fish fossils, travel to the United States.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], December 1, 1848; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866
    Regarding faults. Diagrams referenced are not included in this collection.
  - Letter to Sir Roderick Impey Murchison, September 21, 1853; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864
    Asked publisher to forward a copy of his observations (apologetically classified as a popular work); praise for Murchison's work in Wales.
  - Letter to Sir Roderick [Impey Murchison], August 15, 1854; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865
    Appreciation for Murchison's "extremely valuable and interesting work," which Everett received.
  - Letter to Sir Roderick Impey Murchison, May 23, 1856; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864
    Regrets on the death of Henry de la Beche, confidence in Murchison's stewardship of the Geological Survey, some quid pro quo.
  - Letter to Sir Roderick I[mpey] Murchison, July 9, 1856; Dana, James D. (James Dwight), 1813-1895
    Appreciation for collection of British rocks and fossils; invitation to American Association meeting in August.
  - Letter to Sir Roderick [Impey Murchison], August 10, 1857; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865
    Regrets that, due to health concerns, Murchison canceled his planned trip to the United States.
  - Letter to Sir Rod[erick] I[mpey] Murchison, May 21, 1860; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Letter of introduction for an American mathematician (Peince?)
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey Murchison], February 4, 1861; American Academy of Arts and Sciences
    Appreciation for a collection of U.K. geological maps.
  - Letter to [Sir Roderick Impey] Murchison, September 20, 1861; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866
    Reflections upon Murchison's life, the rise of geology.
  - Letter to Sir Roderick I[mpey] Murchison, September 28, 1867; Campbell, P.
    Regarding coal mining in regions of Newfoundland, Nova Scotia, Cape Breton, and New South Wales.